hi everyone
it's August 1st
and we're in cohort four
having our first discussion on chapter
four
so before we go into more detail on
chapter four and everything
does anyone have any just overall
thoughts or or comments on chapter four
what what did they uh expect it would be
delivering as a chapter
how how was it
or what was any aspect that that people
remembered or anything
um
I uh found this chapter to be rather uh
mathematically dense I suppose and the
authors do warn of that at the beginning
of the chapter
um I mean I think it's great so far as
it starts to introduce how they're using
Bayes theorem
um
how they kind of exploit Jensen's
inequality
to move in the direction of like
calculating uh
free energy
[Music]
using logarithmic functions in order to
do that
um
you know
the initial models of the static
perceptual tasks also seems like a
really nice introduction moving on to
bomb DPS and as well as the continuous
models used in active inference so in a
in a way it felt like it uh kind of
started with nice like first principles
and built up from there but that said I
can start to see maybe the necessity of
having a math learning group for uh some
folks here given this uh chapter
thanks
yeah anyone else any like just overall
thoughts or
well I think yeah I would just totally
agree 100 with what Andrew shared
basically it's just similar thoughts
I mean basically the the maths uh are
very well explained and it goes
gradually but I think it would be
beneficial here to
yeah to go even deeper and slower
through them maybe separately
definitely
any other
thoughts people have
yeah Darius so then anyone else
yeah Daniel it's less a point about the
chapter although I agree with
the previous sentiments that is
mathematically dense it's more of a
point about the mass learning group I
think myself and several others just
having trouble locating it
um
in terms of where it actually is on the
Discord so the past couple of weeks I've
being trying to get into some of the
voice chats and it doesn't there doesn't
seem to be anything kind of happening on
them so
there might be a bit of confusion
yeah thanks well it is uh people can use
the general voice chat just the top
voice Channel
and uh you know if there's no one there
just still jump in and stick in there
okay because otherwise I see sometimes
people jump in and then immediately jump
out and then that then other people
think that there aren't anyone around
so just
jump in and hang in and you'll be able
to see people's like icon and see what
channel they're in
um
I mean yeah it's a it's a it's a
decentralized learning group what I
people can edit Pages or or just ping me
if there's any support needed I'll try
to join what I can
but
it can I mean there's there's so so much
work on the more introductory side
like kind of just going
from the fundamentals
on through
all all the work that Jonathan and Ali
and others are doing too
so there's no no lack of things to do in
math learning group I hope people do
like connect on it
um Young
wait I don't hear you
I can see you're unused
baby Frozen though
can anyone else hear it or no
okay
okay when you're when you're back feel
free to continue
any other um
General thoughts on four or anything
writing in the chat
um
just another small specific observation
that uh as a kind of a practicing
entry-level data scientist uh the way
something that helped me understand the
static perceptual models earlier on is
that it almost feels like it's just
describing something like the process of
binary and classification
yeah
one of the models and uh
figure 4.2 the very first one
you have the example of like uh
your your prior
being a prevalence of a disease
is there a disease yes or no
you have uh your true positive rate your
true negative rate and you end up with
the result of a new test
I found that to be rather interesting
and useful
just are we trying to predict does
someone have a disease or not there's
more that goes into that
step by step
yeah thanks that's that's one of the
classic uh Bayesian
um examples like there's a test that's
99 accurate and there's a disease that
one in ten thousand people have
what is the probability that you have
the disease if you got a positive test
result and the kind of snap answer type
1 answer is um 99 because if it was
positive and it's 99 accurate then how
could it not be 99 but when you actually
unpack the base equation it's actually
not
99 percent
it's actually still unlikely
um in that with those parameters
um young Hoon
oh yeah sorry about that uh
so I I find these mathematical equations
in chapter four to be a little bit
ambiguous
especially like uh the notations or like
Dimensions or whether it's a vector or
whether it's a scalar or
Etc
depending on the context like I find
especially uh difficulty to understand
the exam equation when there are some
functions called like categorical
function so I I just accepted the
concept but
um just wanted to make it more verified
so I actually uploaded some PDF and
questions to the chapter four
because I I got stuck with some
um derivations of it
so that might be in the chord or chapter
four questions and you can look it up
later on
awesome
awesome we'll definitely look at it and
also here I see one this overleaf link
this was prepared wow I guess he just
added this in
this is from Jonathan shock
yes I found it to be very helpful
that's that's awesome
thank you Jonathan
yeah I mean there's even
already there's all there's so many
pieces of material it's it's um
you know it's like a second level
question how we how we
organize things so that they're
discoverable and kind of annotated so
that somebody who's looking for like
this level
of of detail can can connect with this
type of material
let's just read his basic remarks
free energy and expected free energy are
introduced almost in parallel but it's
not clear which one should be used when
or exactly why one needs both of them
this is relatively simple that the free
energy is used to improve the model
itself
whereas the expected free energy is used
to make decisions about which is the
best action to take which will lead to
states which are preferable on states
which lead to more epistemic value which
will themselves themselves allow one to
update the free energy
awesome
yeah this looks really good
um
any other like just thought or question
or area in four that people want to jump
to
yeah young again
oh yeah so I'm I'm not sure whether it's
a good explanation or I'm not sure
whether it's a correct intuition but for
me it feels like
um like comparing with reinforcement
learning uh reducing the free energy is
something a little bit related to
offline learning
while
um
minimizing the expected free energy
seems like to be related to online
learning so
you you choose these decisions and then
you try to reduce the free energy online
or the expected free energy while you
reduce the variation of free energy
offline so
I'm not I'm not saying that those are
equivalents but it seems to me that they
are somehow related
maybe just summarize what is online
offline learning
oh uh not really a master of
reinforcement learning but uh
based on what I understood about it is
that online learning is learning while
you're at doing the action while offline
learning is something more like you
learn the uh value of something based on
the state trajectories that you already
visited so it's more like
learning week by replaying
I would say it can if anyone thinks that
it's I'm explaining it in a very
ambiguous term or if I'm wrong just let
me know
cool yeah you're definitely an area to
look into Darius
I think what might be useful for me and
perhaps others is getting a bit more
clarity on exactly how we Define the
generative model in Acts of inference
so
on one side
um and you hit and you see it expressed
in this chapter that it comprises the
prior
and the likelihood term in base's
equation
um but then on the other I've you know
seen other
theorists talk about how it's actually
basically the entire
um conditioning dependent Dynamics
across the Markov blanket so it includes
the external Dynamics it's not just
what's internally encoded in the
internal states of the particle
so unless that's just a continuing
conflict A continuing debate within the
active inference Community
um
it would be good just to get a little
bit of clarity because I think that also
helps us explain
exactly what is minimizing free energy
and whether we can talk about an agent
having a generative model or being a
generative model
foreign
yes
[Music]
um
it's a great point and
it has come up before so in fact there
are
about one one and a half definitions of
what the generative model is and they're
um they're not identical
they're kind of nested Concepts
and and it certainly does matter and so
I can understand why it's a point of
confusion
um in the 2022 textbook that we're
reading right now
generative model is very very clearly
differentiated from the generative
process
so like when we're looking at the
figures it's like here's a generative
model that's like the agents sometimes
we would call that the particular States
because it it constitutes the whole
particle like just like if we were
talking about a dust particle Browning
motion now we're talking about the
cognitive particle so that includes the
blanket States and the internal States
and so that is sometimes called a
generative model and the generative
model as it's framed in the textbook is
to understand or to make this model of
the generative process which is the
actual process that gives rise to
observations and so this distinction
between generative process and
generative model
is um is heavily used
in the textbook
um
however
more recently
some authors
have have uh taken a slightly difference
approach or definition
so as you mentioned and for example
um
in in this representation
from Maxwell on um
I guess a month ago or something around
then
um
here generative model is used to
describe the entire
particular partition all the States
including the external States
um and in and here's all these questions
um
earlier there was an emphasis on
distinguishing between generative
process and generative model but in this
figure figure one which you've shown the
slides
we don't see any generative process so
where does generative process fit in the
diagram what is the distinction between
the concepts
um
and yeah all all
put these into the coda as well
at least Maxwell is not
um
using the generative model generative
process distinction as much
um
here's how I kind of
reconcile this
whatever you want to call different
parts of the particular partition you
need all four of them to be defined in
the model
so whether you just call them you know
whether you uh buy them a la carte or
whether you buy them in a bundle all the
particular States and the all the states
need to be described
um otherwise you're going to have a null
variable
um and now there's several
um we we could you know we could talk
about uh you know you have your friends
who like this music and you have your
friends who like this food and so there
there's there's different nested levels
of describing the French group with
these four friends one of them is the
way that the textbook describes with the
generative process external only and the
generative model with these three on the
right blanket and internal
another
um group that we talk about sometimes is
just the blanket States
of course states are not intrinsically
blanket States because every state is
blanket is something else and so on but
in this setting blanket and then another
um set of states that we talk about
sometimes are the autonomous States
which is just the internal States and
the active States
autonomous states are the two things
that can be changed
to reduce free energy change your mind
learning perception attention Etc and
action change the world so that's the no
thumb on the scale
so whether or not
you focus on these three on the right
and call it a generative model and this
is a generative process
or whether you call all four the
generative model
at the end of the day the variables are
defined the same way
and the variational and the expected
free energy are still regarding the
autonomous states with respect to the
sensory States and so generative model
and generative process is a little bit
of like a linguistic descriptor or
handle
but it it it
um
it doesn't change anything to give a
different English name to describe a
subset of notes
so I don't think it's an issue however
it is confusing
well I just got one more point of
clarification on that yeah yeah
you go back to that diagram that would
be quite useful actually
here so yeah that's perfect
um in terms of self-evidencing then
if we take Maxwell's idea that it's
degenerative model is the system the
across the Markov blanket do we talk
could one consider that system to be
self-evidencing or is it only the
particle which excludes the external
states which is self-evidencing
that's a great question I think also
calls back to your
um rock climbing
example okay the rock climber is uh
doing something cognitive about the wall
but is the wall doing something
cognitive about the climber or is there
some
are we considering the entire system as
doing some kind of gradient descents
yeah that's it's a good um question
either side of the blanket
I believe may be seen as doing some kind
of self-evidising now in the case of
um
one active
adoptive sentient entity
and one inert one
the inert entities self evidencing is
going to be
um trivial
so just because there's um
self-evenancing on both sides of the mic
it doesn't mean it's the same kind of
self-evidising
but you can also make situations where
it is the same kind of self evidencing
across both sides like in the bird song
example
does that uh do two or uh when when two
sentient agents are engaged in
self-evidencing
does that constitute
higher uh level of self-evidencing at
the entire system level description
possibly
I I mean if if um
if they're both reducing free energy now
what if one is
um reducing free energy and that is
creating an increase in free energy for
the other
could that increase the net free energy
on the system I I don't know
or is it always the case that that it um
that the ball has to roll downhill and
the more massive cognitively massive
self-evidencer
takes a stronger hand and and that makes
it move down on average also I don't
know
Andrew
I don't wanna
pull too far away from the kind of
current formulation that's being
discussed here but something that
um has been useful for me and it I think
I please correct me if I'm misstating
this but uh with differentiating the
generative model and the generative
process and part is that the generative
model is presumed to have
um something like preferences or the the
its own C Matrix or its own homeostatic
set points which I believe the
generative process does not have so we
have like from chapter three and so on
and the generative process or the
environment of the the agent the
generative model is presumed to have
like you know dissipative forces entropy
and so on and so the generative model is
kind of acting against those in order to
realize its own
uh expectations or preferences that is
uh I I want to survive as a generative
model the environment around me has no
set of direct preferences saying like
Andrew needs to survive I'm the one
who's saying that and so despite the
fact that I'm attempting to uh infer or
approximate the external States so that
I can get around in the world like I'm
also kind of acting against it or or at
least you know in a way that doesn't
it's never going to exactly equate to
the the generative process around me and
this is where the map does not equal the
territory uh kind of uh formulation
starts to come into play and becomes all
the more
is any of that track yeah that that's a
it's a great
um points
um certainly map doesn't have to be the
territory even structurally like the
generative model too cold just right too
hot three state categorical that's the
categorical distribution or it could be
um uh continuous variable zero to one or
zero to 100 and then outside it could be
a totally different structure and so the
generative process I I believe it or if
you just call it you know the process
generating observations
that could just be a sine wave or it
could be a square wave or it could be a
deterministic
um system and so that that makes it very
clear like like you said that when we're
talking about the generative model of
the agents we're talking about a b c d e
those are the variables that have to be
defined that's figure 4.3 basically what
whether we're working in continuous time
or in um
uh discrete time
these are the variables that have to be
defined or counted for in the generative
model
this doesn't describe how those
observations are generated
so this is kind of like just the agent
lifted from the environment and so it
still is helpful and it's the one that's
exerting preference and engaging in
sentient behavior and all of that and
then it's like helpful again whether you
call it generative process or
underlying process generating the
observations or the components of the
system that generate the agent's
observations
just to make it clear that we're not
always in a situation where it's two
active entities talking to each other
like the bird song example but rather we
can be in a situation where
um like the rock climber that Darius
brought up where you have like
this figure 4.3 agents
and then
there can be an articulation with a
generative process again or whatever you
want to call it that is
not doing like policy selection
except in a trivial way
yeah these are all great points and and
it's funny you know it reflects
how things update and and evolve
and helps us get a get a parallax
on on what's really
happening what are like just the purely
verbal descriptors
we're actually like the term like the
English term isn't doing any work
like generative model generative process
the term doesn't necessarily do any work
what what does do work though
is statements like this
calculation of free energy requires data
why
family of variational distribution
Q
and the generative model
those three things together can get a
free energy
and that also helps reveal like why
discussion of well when this happens
then the free energy would go up those
are speculative statements they can be
super useful and interesting but until
the calculation has occurred
it would be like
um talking about a linear aggression
that hasn't been performed or talking
about a time series analysis that hasn't
been performed
so it makes it clear where's the
conversational and the speculative
and then how do we get to a point where
we can calculate the free energy
about the data with respect to the
distributions
equation 2.5
variational free energy
about the variational distribution and
the data
so that's how we get there
any other kind of thoughts on four
also Ellie and a few people probably
have watched it but just a few days ago
Ollie and I did a video overview on four
um
well we can um turn to a question
that someone has
um
okay both these questions look very good
and they're later slightly later
in the chapter and slightly
um with the math details
um I wonder if Jonathan's work May
address some of this but we'll try to
get there
let's start a little earlier
um on
and also yeah people can can um upvote
the questions so that we can pick a
place to start but
um does anyone have a specific question
they want to bring up
or do we want to walk through like
through and and just get to just see
what the sections are about
okay
um
Bayesian brain
describes using Bayesian statistics well
there's sort of an instrumentalist
flavor and a realist flavor as with many
things the realist flavor would be the
brain does Bayesian statistics which
might be very deep might be very
um overreaching the instrumentalist
flavor is
we can model what the brain is doing
with Bayesian statistics which is to say
like updating
what kinds of Bayesian statistics well
the inbound sense making signal
processing side
and then the outbound action selection
control theory side
two operations of kind of the general
cybernetic entity
and we can use Bayesian models Bayesian
methods
there
um that's the problem of inferring
states of the world perception inbound
sense making and inferring the course of
action
action selection outbound planning
exact inference is generally
computationally intractable or
infeasible
separate from that limitation
in psychology
often what's being considered is bounded
rationality or like constraint Limited
cognition
so how can we respect that we're
modeling bounded rationality approximate
rationality
limited finite systems
and kind of
um at the same time
um move Beyond this limitation of exact
base being intractable
um like in the uh frog jumping out of
the hand example
it was just some small matrices to
multiply and so the exact base in
calculation was not out of our grasp
however if we were going to be doing
um
some kind of large-scale data analysis
then
of course we would need to do some
approximation methods
um
there's two
large just just speaking broadly there's
two ways to approach this kind of
approximate Bayesian
uh calculation
and they're related and there there's
many many sub-flavers and live stream 52
is a good place to learn more about this
but there's sampling methods and
variational methods
sampling based methods or Monte Carlo
methods that came from the card games
that were played in Monte Carlo and it
was like well like what's the
probability of getting
um two twos uh four red cards and one
clubs
I mean you could write an expression and
try to analytically solve that
the UR the sampling based approach which
has become called the Monte Carlo
approach is where you just draw
um hands of cards and then you draw a
million hands and you say okay then
there's three so then in the end you say
my best estimate is this happens three
out of a million times
now
you can probably see a lot of um like
limitations
but advantages of sampling on one hand
it allows you to approximate arbitrary
potentially analytically unruly
distributions
so even where you don't have a nice
smooth function or you don't know a lot
about the system sampling may work quite
well on the other hand you never really
know if you're sampling appropriately or
if you've sampled the completion
the other methods that are utilized and
also this cannot be done incrementally
very well at all you need to curate many
many many samples
in order to make an estimate
and where State spaces are large like
the state spaces of all
genomic diversity for an animal with a
billion base pairs in its genome there's
going to be certain things where it's
just not really tractable
um
in contrast variational methods
are an information Theory driven
approach
that is going to use all the tools that
will come to know and love like the KL
Divergence and and the variational free
energy so that's kind of like why we're
taking this path at all because exact
Bays would be epic but it's intractable
exact base would allow us to compute the
minimum surprise model which would be
the maximum evidence model
we're not going to be able to compute
exact base in general
how can we approximate it well with
sampling and or variational
sampling has some situational advantages
but variational is a much much more
flexible approach it's a lot more
tractable it's incrementally optimizable
we can reduce the KL Divergence and
improve our model fit
incrementally and kind of indubitably
like we will always make the fit better
if we reduce the kale Divergence we're
making the fit better
now that doesn't mean that the final fit
or anywhere along the way is adequate
for your business your company or you
know whatever you could be moving a
gaussian distribution to its best
possible fit location in the middle of a
bimodal distribution
and still be totally missing the point
so this isn't to say like it works it's
just to say the ball rolls downhill
that's like the big picture on why
variational methods are being used so
chapter four is going to describe
generative models
which are using Bayesian networks using
Bayesian methods to describe cognitive
systems sense making an action
and then the variational methods
are going to support us
doing optimization and inference with
these models
approaching exact base
asymptotically
but instead of focusing on surprise
minimization itself
um which we're not going to be able to
directly calculate
um
we're going to be able to calculate
something that is bounding surprise
and that's going to be the variational
free energy
and in figure 2.4 we kind of saw what
that looked like as well
variational free energy equation 2.5
the distributions and the data
and if we can shrink that Divergence
we're getting ratcheting closer to
surprise
so that's why it's possible to use
variational free energy to incrementally
optimize and update and learn
and use that um
attractively
Jensen's inequality would be awesome to
have more of a um
uh like an unpacking on this because
this is kind of um
it's very provocative in general
but suffice to say that because of the
curvature
of the natural log function or any other
function that's concave down like that
um
were then able to use that property of
this curvature type function
and properties of logs
in order to generate
an inequality
such that the log of the expectation
is always greater than the expectation
of the log
so it's kind of like an application of
Jensen's inequality for concave down
functions in this setting
to
heuristic bounding
of what what we would really want to
know
there's some further rearranging
um again I'll review later perhaps
Jonathan's um writing makes this uh
clear or other people can can fill in
some dots
um but
where this is all kind of like more
detail on equation 2.5
just helping us understand variational
free energy
as kind of like the Bayesian optimal way
to fit um where's Jonathan's writings uh
on the chapter four page it is um here
and I'll put it in the chat thank you
Kate
so that was 4.2
section 4.2 was just saying
Bayesian inference
frog jumping out of the hands if you can
calculate it exactly go for it No One's
Gonna Stop you but in situations where
we want to do it
approximatable heuristic
and one that's incrementally optimizable
we can use free energy this is also
known as energy-based methods or
energy-based learning or variational
methods going back to decades ago so
this is not invented by active inference
at all it's also called the evidence
lower Bound in Bayesian statistics
and so this is just applying that
methodology
approximate Bayesian computation
with a variational flavor not the
sampling flavor
to
in this case
the question of perception
now
you know having made the the software
update from just pure exact base to
approximate base
now we can calculate the free energy
for a generative model
so whereas an exact base we would be
talking about getting the maximum
evidence model minimum surprise model
plug and Chuck
now we're going to get the minimum free
energy
model
which is going to be
converging towards that minimum surprise
maximum
evidence
um the book is going to return and
continue to juxtapose and contrast
two major architectural decisions that
are made for dynamical models now not
all models are dynamical not all models
involve something changing through time
but
in general when you are modeling
something that's changing Through Time
you can either have a continuous time
model or a discrete time model
discretization sometimes still has to
come into play for continuous models and
so on
but this is like the two broad
approaches to dealing with dynamical
systems continuous time discrete time
and that's why figure 4.3 we're always
coming back to again and again with the
discrete time and with A continuous time
because it's like a Rosetta Stone that's
like saying whether you take this
approach to modeling time or that
approach
there are some consequences
and there's different settings where
they may be more or less appropriate but
we're still talking about the same
infrastructure and logic
for generative models
but before building up to 4.3
which has this like downstairs
perception passive perceptual inference
component and then an upstairs decision
making component and analogously for
continuous time
figure 4.2 is just getting us familiar
with what these um causal graph
structures are and do
and so it's a fun exercise or question
like to first off draw
um different situations that you're
interested in or thinking of as like
Bayesian causal graphs
and then also to look at the ones
provided here
and then think about what real world
situations map onto these like maybe
here's was there a lightning strike or
not unobserved but then we observe the
light and the sounds
or there could be other examples but but
this is just kind of like bring the
level of rigor
to causal flowchart mapping
and these are really extensible and
composable like you can connect them in
many different ways
and given their connectivity
you've defined like the necessary and
sufficient information for that model
it's not like oh and there's a secret
connection from you know this one back
to that one it's like what's written is
there and included and calculated with
standard methods
what's not included isn't included it'd
be like
a calculator it um is only going to add
what you tell it's at
so inference is going to proceed along
this infrastructure
without some other secret third thing
influencing it
so they they talk a bit more about just
what what these um how to read the
relationships between different
variables
then they get to figure 4.3
which is
the Rosetta Stone figure between the
discrete time and the continuous time
um anyone want to give a thought or a
question on figure 4.3
well we're going to return to the
contrasts of
discrete time and continuous time
multiple times it's going to come back
most fully in chapter 7 and chapter 8
which are wholly dedicated to discrete
and continuous time but in this section
it's going to foreshadow and discuss
those two different types Darius
presumably this model
um is a kind of
simplification of what might be going on
in the cognitive creature I because I
presume there are some backward loops in
which the observations that you make are
informing your action policy
hence the action perception Loop
um
similarly I was also I also make the
presumption that the state dependencies
have to be informed by prior action
policies and beliefs so priors about
these so I presume it's just this
architecture needs to be built out a
little bit more or else it's not really
governed by any particular Telos by any
particular
incentive
yeah great points
um
there is a prior
that helps get the ball rolling
um and and so that prior kind of starts
the chain
but then in subsequent
um time steps the the action and the
unfolding of the situation at the prior
time Point
um sets how things are
um
and certainly these are like
these are like uh
like a frame it does not have more
advanced cognitive features like
attention anticipation
[Music]
so on those things get get layered in
but this is kind of like the kernel or
like The Motif that we then can can
elaborate and bring richness to and so
that's like why sometimes there's an
adjective in front of active inference
like sophisticated active inference or
deep active inference affective active
inference and those adjectives call
attention
to certain structural
motifs that are being brought into play
and this is kind of like this is like
the lowest common denominator
because we have
a prior on hidden state was a prior on
the temperature of the room and then we
have the temperature of the room
changing Through Time
and the thermometer readings emitted at
each time
that's the downstairs passive inference
bit D is a prior
hidden State real temperature B
describes how temperatures change
Through Time a describes the
relationship between
temperature emitting observations or
observations inferring back to
temperature downstairs
looking like an e facing down
passive inference
where do we embed action in The
partially observable Markov decision
process well the partially observable
part is on the bottom
because we have parts that are
observable and parts that aren't so it's
partially observable
the markovian property through time is
that the past only influences the future
through the present
partially observable Markov and then the
last piece is the decision process
Pi is your policy it's intervening in
how the world changes Through Time
and
what guides policy selection well you
could make a pomdp that has a stochastic
policy selection or has reward driven
policy selection or as we're going to
see we utilize expected free energy to
guide policy selection so this is kind
of bringing the well-known pomdp format
to bear on our setting Young
yeah so I'm a bit confused about this
generated model because
as you said it's a generative model so
do you it does this model actually mean
that it's uh we're doing some kind of
commenting process about this because
um to what I understood is that uh
number one number two and number three
which is like the maybe the number three
which should be notated as the
transition metrics uh or a policy pie is
actually something that is like a real
dynamics of the external world not
something that we are estimating so
that's that's something that I'm being
confused so because if you're saying
generator model it means it sounds to me
like it's something that is happening in
our brain but in what I understood was
that this is a diagram about the
external World itself
great great
question so in fact we see two
representations
um one of them is the particular
partition looking representation with
the four internal and external blanket
States
here
we don't see external States at all
and it's not even shown like where they
connect in
and this is actually all happening
within the
um cognitive model of the agent I think
the figure that that clarifies this the
most is nine point
one
so now we're pulling back to the
behavioral experimenters lab so here's
going to be the rat in the maze
we are using the pomdp
um architecture
to make a model of the rats beliefs
about temperature changing through time
and its beliefs about how policy
influences that
its beliefs about how temperature and
thermometer are linked
so the pomdp
is describing the the
agents
parameterization
it is not the actual true unfolding of
the system
here the observations are being actually
the generative process is in this outer
layer
if we want to think about it that way
um so yes the the B Matrix is something
that the agent learns
about how States change through time and
how its actions intervene
but it is that's not actually
how things change Through Time
that that that's tracked by another
variable yeah
oh yeah so does it mean that those uh
EP
function annotation key should be
actually Q because it's an approximation
isn't it
so like
uh I don't really remember which chapter
it was but maybe chapter two the diagram
actually kind of shows that he is
actually a
annotation for the notation for the uh
probability happening in the real
external World while two is something
that we approximate so basically I think
it's it's better it's much more accurate
to say uh Q Pi q o given as
Etc
yes I I
would like to see someone else also
um check on that however yeah I believe
it makes sense to think about these as
as the belief distributions of the agent
and hence utilize Q
whereas here p is just being used as
like a generic statistical distribution
but but I I am not 100 confident on that
but
I I agree and that's that is how we
think about it from the agent's
perspective
and I'll I I agree that the q's and the
P's you know mind your q's and P's it
does get confusing because it's like
well wait but if we know anything about
p
why are we not just like using that
information like why are we even messing
around with Q if we can contrast it with
with p
so these like minor
um notation ambiguity is actually making
me kind of confused about the equations
so I just wanted to clear
well in the um
I
I would love to help
connect
the ontology terms which then we can
support with translations and everything
to the equations and to the difference
representations
because I I agree and
um
the equations work out and then second
layer renderings or schematics
often include or exclude things that
that reduce the clarity of what they're
representing
um well in the rest of four discrete
time
is explored more that's basically more
math about the top part of figure four
three
section four five continuous time more
math on the bottom of figure four three
some extremely
um spicy and interesting topics with
Markov blankets and message passing
and some representations of message
passing
generalized coordinates of motion
and some visualizations about that
connecting it to Taylor series expansion
LaPlace approximation another tool in
the toolbox
to help approximate
a given inference problem by using a
quadratic expansion around the mode
more message passing
and that's the end of four
so definitely it's a dense chapter most
of the density is in this second half of
four
where it's just giving a lot more detail
on discrete time and on continuous time
and the big picture is we're introducing
the kernel or the minimal Motif and some
of the mechanics
associated with using discrete time and
continuous time models
so next time
um
we will turn to the cohort for questions
so it'd be awesome if people add
questions
and and vote them
and we'll come back and take it from
there
okay
any last thoughts
okay thank you
very well everybody bye